This quote is beautiful, but there's
another level to it because cinema
doesn't behave like the real world at
all. It doesn't really fixate reality as
much as it remodels it.
It slows it down,
speeds it up,
reverses it,
and most importantly for this video,
it completely rearranges it. To
understand what I mean, consider this
moment from Damien Chazelle's Whiplash
and try to clock just how many
perspectives your brain is forced to
weld together.
Six. Six different perspectives in about
6 seconds.
That's what cinema does. It turns
fragments into fluid moments. But these
perspectives were all captured in the
same physical space. It's easier for us
to visually connect them. So, let's dig
deeper. Have a look at this moment from
the opening of Denis Villeneuve's
Sicario. Yes, I'm talking about Sicario
again.
We approach the house from the
perspective of the FBI's armored vehicle
and then we cut to this perspective from
inside the house so we can experience
this guy's shock as the vehicle breaches
the wall. These two shots fit together
in our minds almost as if they happen in
one continuous moment, but they weren't
captured that way. This shot was filmed
on location and this shot was filmed on
a set built specifically to allow this
fake armored truck to bust through this
fake wall as spectacularly as it does.
Two shots, two locations, two separate
moments in time stitched into one
seamless experience. This isn't how our
reality works, and yet here in the world
of moving pictures, it's a mechanism we
actively rely on to make sense of what
we're experiencing. Renowned film editor
Walter Murch said something along these
same lines in his book In the Blink of
an Eye.
It's pretty damn good. The cut actually
does seem to work, even though it
represents a total and instantaneous
displacement of one field of vision with
another.
A displacement that sometimes also
entails a jump forward or backward in
time as well as space.
It works, but it could easily have been
otherwise, since nothing in our
day-to-day experience seems to prepare
us for such a thing.
Murch is pointing at something deep
here, something fundamental to our
experience of moving pictures beyond
even the familiar 24 frames per second
illusion often cited in these
discussions. That's just extraordinary.
You see the one on the other side? That
editing is a kind of unnatural
reality-altering movement that shouldn't
work, but does. And that's because
cinema hijacks a deeper mechanism, our
instinct to assume continuity.
In the context of cinematic
storytelling, when one discontinuous
image follows another, we don't
experience fragments, we experience
flow. We instinctively connect what we
see, inferring cause, sequence, and
meaning, even when none of these are
explicitly shown.
Editing doesn't just depend on this
instinct, it weaponizes it. Cuts don't
feel like ruptures because our
perception smooths them over, and
filmmakers actively reinforce that
smoothing with more than just images.
Sound bridges, for instance, are one of
the strongest tools we have for that.
Anchoring us in a continuous space as
images fracture. Here's a really good,
but easily missed example of this from
Christopher Nolan's The Prestige.
This change in perspective from the
audience to beneath the stage is fairly
drastic in spatial terms, and it works
for a number of reasons. One big one
being that prior scenes have helped to
establish our spatial expectations. But,
a more fascinating reason is a detail
most people don't consciously notice.
But, that's kind of the point, because
our brains do notice. It's this, the
applause, which doesn't just continue,
it transforms and shifts our oral
perspective along with our visual
perspective.
This cut may move us, changing what we
see and where we are, but it's the sound
that carries us and keeps the world
intact.
And that's just one way in which
cinema's language tricks and coerces our
brains into maintaining continuity,
keeping us orientated in stories amongst
a barrage of discontinuous imagery.
Other technical components do the same.
Camera movement, cutting on action,
consistent blocking and spatial cues,
for example, are all tools that
filmmakers use to quietly reinforce this
illusion of continuity, like in this
pair of shots from Francis Ford
Coppola's Apocalypse Now. A simple
camera pan directs our gaze, and a cut
on the action of lifting the pack of
cigarettes shifts our perspective whilst
maintaining our orientation. What these
examples boil down to is this simple
fact. Cinema works because your brain
does the stitching. When cutting is done
well, we we perceive the temporal and
spatial dissonance.
My son has felt the
unless we're meant to.
It's the key to smaller moments and
bigger ones like this, where A flows
perfectly into B because there are
logical, visual, and kinetic connections
between both shots. There's continuity.
And this phenomenon also works for
sequences that violate chronology, such
as this one in Christopher Nolan's
Oppenheimer.
This time there was another man.
Said his name was Pash. Pash?
You met Colonel Pash? Colonel Pash could
be A sequence that is constructed from
three different timelines and several
different conversations rapidly
overlapping one another. We remain
orientated across time here largely
because the sound doesn't fracture with
the image. Through well-placed J-cuts
and a sustained score, music and
dialogue flow seamlessly together,
meaning that when the timeline shift,
our train of thought doesn't. is who's
an acquaintance of someone on the
project.
And you thought Pash would be satisfied
with that? I was attempting to give them
Alperton without opening a can of worms.
I told them a cock-and-bull story. You
lied to General Groves, too. No.
I admitted to him that I lied to Pash.
Do you recall this conversation about
the Chevalier incident?
I've seen so many versions of it. Um
wasn't confused before, but I'm
certainly getting there now. With this
auditory information in place, the
overall experience feels continuous. As
a result, the frequent temporal leaps
and changes in perspective are far less
disruptive. On a basic level, these are
all examples of how films manipulate our
perception to guide us. They exploit our
brains' hunger for continuity to
construct a flowing experience from
images that are in reality fragmented
across time and space.
Yeah.
And remarkably, it works. Discontinuous
parts resolve into a continuous whole in
our minds.
>> kid earned everything once.
It is extraordinary, and it's one of the
reasons why filmmaking is such a
uniquely powerful art form. This is a
medium built on rearranging reality,
where the native language is temporal
and spatial manipulation. Every cut
fractures time, moving us either
forwards or backwards. My nose is
already broke.
Every change in framing is a reshaping
of space. A change of angle or
perspective can teleport us around the
room.
While things like dynamic camera
movement can alter the spatial
relationships between us and subjects in
the blink of an eye. The use of
miniatures and CGI fabricates spaces
that don't really exist.
Days, hours, months, and years collapse
into minutes or even seconds, and we
don't bat an eye. That is, until we're
emotionally beaten over the head with
it. And today I'm the age you were when
you left.
This is the grammar of filmmaking, and
it's present in every single one of our
viewing experiences, and I mean all of
them. Films like Interstellar and Happy
Gilmore are comparable. Both belong to
the same species. Both reshape our
perception of time and space through the
everyday grammar of cinema. The fact
that one pushes things further and in
doing so achieve something significantly
more profound is a topic for the next
video. For now, the crucial point is
this. Before we even get into asking
what makes the big, bold, and obviously
mind-bending manipulations of time and
space so powerful,
we need to realize that everything we
watch is already doing it.
Tarkovsky was right. Films are mosaics
of time.
But they're also mosaics of space, of
perspective, of sound, of moments
captured separately and stitched
together into something that feels
whole.
It isn't fixated reality. It's
deliberately and invisibly rearranged
reality. And the only reason it works is
because of the astonishing complexity of
our own mental machinery.
That's it. That's the trick. And now
you've seen it,
you won't be able to unsee it.
You're welcome.
Thank you very much for watching.